So today's דף daf. *daf* is נ"ח *nun ches*, the penultimate דף
*daf* of the מסכת *masechet*. I just like saying penultimate. We pick
up with three lines from the top of נ"ח *nun ches*, and
we're still discussing this question about whether they would do the, what
they would do for every separate מוסף Musaf *musaf*, if it was
a day that had a coincidence of different מוספים musafim *musafim*, would
they have separate blasts of the חצוצרות *chatzotzrot* for each מוסף Musaf,
*musaf*? It's also a question whether they would have a different שיר
של יום *shir shel yom* for each מוסף Musaf *musaf*. So let's
take a look. And the claim is yes, but we'll see where
this is ending. מיתיבי *Meitvei* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* on this:
דתני רבה בר שמואל *D'tani Rabba Bar Shmuel*, יכול כשם שתוקעין על
שבת Shabbat בפני עצמה ועל ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh בפני עצמו *Yachol
k'shem shetokin al Shabbat bifnei atzmah v'al Rosh Chodesh bifnei atzmo*, we
taught the ברייתא Baraita: *braita*, perhaps the same way you have a
separate blast, blasts for the שבת מוסף Musaf *Shabbat Musaf* by itself
and ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* by itself, maybe when they coincide you'll
have separate blasts for each one? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar, ובראשי חדשיכם
*Talmud lomar u'vroshei chodsheichem*, אני ראש חודש *Ani Rosh Chodesh*. Now how
exactly that proves otherwise we'll discuss in a minute, but clearly the
intent of that ברייתא Baraita? *braita* is to say you do not
have separate blasts for each separate מוסף Musaf. *musaf*. תיובתא דרבי אחא
תיובתא *Tiyuvta d'Rabbi Akha tiyuvta*. So that's a complete contradiction of רבי
Rabbi אחא *Rabbi Akha*. That ברייתא *braita* is clearly saying you do
not have separate חצוצרות *chatzotzrot* blasts for each separate מוסף Musaf. *musaf*.
Not so fast. Well no, it's clear that's what it's trying to
prove. Now the question is how does it prove it from the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*? So אמר אביי Abaye אמר קרא k'ra *Amar Abaye
amar Kra*, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says ובראשי חדשיכם *u'vroshei chodsheichem*. Okay,
what does that mean? הוקשו כל החדשים כולם זה לזה *Hukshu kol
hachodashim kulam zeh lazeh*. So all of your בראשי חדשיכם *u'vroshei chodsheichem*,
they're all in one category, which means that whether it's a normal
ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh*, or whether it's a ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh*
that is also שבת *Shabbat*, whether it's a ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh*
that's also ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, *Rosh Hashanah*, you're only going to
do one set of blasts. This is by the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
that talks about the חצוצרות *chatzotzrot* blasts. It says וביום שמחתכם ובמועדיכם
ובראשי חדשיכם ותקעתם בחצצרת על עלתיכם ועל זבחי שלמיכם *u'v'yom simchatchem u'v'moadeichem
u'v'roshei chodsheichem u'tekatem bachatzotzrot al oloteichem
v'al zivchei shalmeichem*. So here's the פסוק *pasuk* that talks about doing
the חצוצרות *chatzotzrot* blasts on the ימים טובים *Yamim Tovim*, and it
says ובראשי חדשיכם *u'vroshei chodsheichem* as a category. All the בראשי חדשיכם
*u'vroshei chodsheichem* are treated the same, so even if it's a שבת
ראש חודש *Shabbos Rosh Chodesh*, even if it's a ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah ראש חודש *Rosh Hashanah Rosh Chodesh*, it's all the same and
all gets one set of blasts. So that's where we learn it
from. That's a pretty good read. רב אשי אמר כתיב חדשכם *Rav
Ashi amar ksiv chodsh'chem* without the יוד *yud*, וכתיב ובראשי *v'ksiv u'vroshei*,
so again playing on a קרי וכתיב *kri u'ksiv*, ובראשי *u'vroshei* is
plural, חדשכם *chodsh'chem* is singular without the יוד *yud*. So איזו חודש
שיש לו שני sheni, ראשים *Eizu chodesh sheyesh lo shenei rashim*? So
what's one that's both a single and a double? So it's one
ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* that is a double, that has two ראשים
*rashim*. So what is that? הוי אומר זה ראש השנה *Hevei omer
zeh Rosh Hashanah*. It's ראש החודש *Rosh Hachodesh* and it's ראש השנה
*Rosh Hashanah*. אמר רחמנא חדשכם *Amar Rachmana chodsh'chem*, but it's treated as
one, חדא היא *chada hi*, so you treat it as a single.
Okay, so it's a little bit funny how to get it from
the פסוק *pasuk*, whether to read the פסוק *pasuk* as talking about
ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*, or reading the פסוק *pasuk* as just putting
everything in the same category. But nevertheless the פשט *pshat* is clear
that you only have one set of שופר *shofar* blasts even when
you have multiple מוספים *musafim*. ועוד תניא *V'od tanya*, we have another
ברייתא *braita*. בחול המועד בראשון barishon מה היו אומרים hayu omerim *Bechol
hamoed barishon mah hayu omrim*, so this is the שיר של יום
*shir shel yom* that they would say on סוכות Succos, *Sukkot*. So
let's take a look. Do we have a תנ"ך *Tanach* here?
Take a look a bit if we have a תנ"ך *Tanach*,
we did have a תנ"ך *Tanach*, I think it's... oh, it doesn't
matter, we know תהילים Tehillim? *Tehillim*.
Okay,
so this is what they would say on the different שיר של
יום *shir shel yom* of חול המועד Chol HaMoed *chol hamoed*. By
the way, you know, it's interesting as you might know, the מנהג
הגר"א Minhag HaGra *minhag haGra*, I think the מנהג ספרדים *minhag Sefardim*
is to say on the special days, like יום טוב Yom Tov,
*Yom Tov*, חול המועד Chol HaMoed *chol hamoed*, etc., that for the
שיר של יום *shir shel yom* of the day, to say the
one of the special one they would say, not the one for
the day of the week. I don't know, there might be some
places I don't remember that do both, the day of the week
and the special one. Anyway, I think the מנהג הגר"א *minhag haGra*
is only to do the special one. But the reality is that
you would do, you would have actually multiple opportunities as we're learning,
for not for מוסף *Musaf*, for מוסף *Musaf* that's the whole issue,
that if you have multiple מוספים *musafim* you'd have to pick one
to say. Before we said, right, when it was for example ראש
חודש שבת *Rosh Chodesh Shabbat*, the simple ברייתא *braita* before what said,
only the ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh*, because that's where we're heading right
now to say you only do one שיר של יום *shir shel
yom*, you only do one set of תקיעות *tekiot*, but that would
be for the מוסף *Musaf*. For the תמיד Tamid, *Tamid* you'd still
say the regular one that you would say for the תמיד Tamid
*Tamid*. So you have, you know, this so you've got this question
about like which of the שיר של יום *shir shel yom* to
be saying in our current דאווענינג *davening*. And there's the difference: we
say the normal one and the מנהג הגר"א *minhag haGra* is...
On ראש חודש you say one for plus today. Right, that's true,
that's true.
On ראש חודש we do say we do we do say two.
That is correct. Okay, so what would they say? So it says
the following. It says
that בחוה"מ bechol hamoed בראשון the first day of חול המועד Chol
HaMoed, היו אומרים הבו לה' בני אילים. Havu L'hashem Bnei Eilim.
Now what is the significance of these various תהילים? So a lot
of them have to do with—well, let's take a look. A lot
are connected to the gifts to the poor, the agricultural gifts to
the poor that would be unique for—that would be a special מצוות
mitzvot particularly around סוכות, Succos. which is when you're gathering in all
the grain from the field. But let's take a look at what
they are. So this, the first one is מזמור כ"ט, Mizmor Kaf
Tes, הבו לה' בני אילים הבו לה' כבוד ועוז, Havu L'hashem Bnei
Eilim Havu L'hashem Kavod Va'oz, right? השתחוו לה' בהדרת קודש, Hishtachavu L'hashem
Behadrat Kodesh, so
bowing down to God in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay. So
then, but then it gets to קול ה' על המים א-ל הכבוד
הרעים ה' על מים רבים, Kol Hashem Al Hamayim Keil Hakavod Hir'im
Hashem Al Mayim Rabim, right?
So there you have the clear tie-in to the water, which is
clearly a major theme of סוכות. Succos, So that would be day
one. What would be the next one? בשני מה היו אומרים? Besheini
Mah Hayu Omerim? What would they say on the second day? So
ולרשע אמר א-לוהים. V'larasha Amar Elokim.
Now what does that have to do with anything? So let's take
a look. תהילים נ'... Tehillim Nun...
one minute. So there, hold on, let me just check how רש"י
Rashi explains it.
Right. So anyway, so רש"י—so Rashi there it's more of a—of a
very—of one of תוכחה, tochecha,
of remonstrating, and there it speaks about like, you know, one of
these—here I'll just read you, it says like this: ק-ל א-לוהים ה'
דיבר ויקרא ארץ ממזרח שמש עד מבואו. מציון מכלל יופי א-לוהים הופיע.
יבוא א-לוהינו ואל יחרש אש לפניו תאכל וסביביו נשערה מאד. יקרא אל
השמים מעל ואל הארץ לדין עמו. אספו לי חסידי כורתי בריתי עלי
זבח. ויגידו שמים צדקו כי א-לוהים שופט הוא סלה. שמעה עמי ואדברה
ישראל ואעידה בך א-לוהים א-לוהיך אנכי. לא על זבחיך אוכיחך ועולותיך לנגדי
תמיד. לא אקח מביתך פר ממכלאותיך עתודים. כי לי כל חיית יער
בהמות בהררי אלף. ידעתי כל עוף הרים וזיז שדי עמדי. אם ארעב
לא אומר לך כי לי תבל ומלואה. האוכל בשר אבירים ודם עתודים
אשתה. זבח לא-לוהים תודה ושלם לעליון נדריך. וקראני ביום צרה אחלצך ותכבדני.
Keil Elokim Hashem diber vayikra aretz mimizrach shemesh ad mevo'o. Mitziyon michlal
yofi Elokim hofia. Yavo Elokeinu veal yecherash esh lefanav tochal usevivav nis'ara
meod. Yikra el hashamayim meal veel haaretz ladin amo. Isfu li chasidai
krotei veriti alei zavach. Vayagidu shamayim tzidko ki Elokim shofet hu sela.
Shima ami vaadabeira Yisrael vaa'ida bach Elokim Elokecha anochi. Lo al zvachecha
ochichecha veolotecha lenegdi tamid. Lo ekach mibeitecha far mimichleotecha atudim. Ki li
chol chayat ya'ar behemot behararei alef. Yadati chol of harim veziz sadai
imadi. Im erev lo omar lach ki li tevel umloah. Haochal besar
abirim v'dam atudim eshteh. Zvach L'elokim todah veshalem
L'elyon nedarecha. Ukra'eni beyom tzara achaltzecha utchabdani. Okay, ולרשע אמר א-לוהים מה
לך לספר חוקי ותשא בריתי עלי פיך. V'larasha Amar Elokim Mah Lecha
Lesaper Chukai Vatisa Veriti Alei Picha.
So this is really, with his—this is an interesting מזמור mizmor that
is both on the one hand sort of saying, what do I
need your sacrifices for?
As we know, sometimes a theme, you know, it's about your good
deeds, but it also says pay up to God your vows with
your קרבנות. korbanot. So
רש"י—so Rashi רש"י Rashi says that it's focusing on that verse and
it's talking about the issue that if you're coming to the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you know, the time of the רגלים Regalim was
the time that you had to make good on vows you made
during the year. If you passed a certain number of רגלים, Regalim,
you transgressed בל תאחר, bal te'acher, postponing your vows. So רש"י Rashi
says the focus is on that verse about pay up your vows,
but you could also say the focus on the verses, you know,
don't overly focus on the sacrifices, focus on the more, you know,
general religious and ethical behavior. So that is that verse. It's not
a direct tie-in to סוכות, Succos? but more generally about coming to
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. בשלישי מה היו אומרים? Beshelishi Mah Hayu
Omerim? What would they say on the third day? מי יקום לי
עם מרעים? Mi Yakum Li Im Mere'im? Okay, so what's that about?
So—so that, the verse that רש"י... Rashi...
one minute. רש"י Rashi there says, let me just read—read you some
selections from that, צ"ד. Tzadik Dalet.
Okay,
so that's א-ל נקמות ה' א-ל נקמות הופיע, Keil Nekamot Hashem Keil
Nekamot Hofia, הנשא שופט הארץ השב גמול על גאים, Hinasei Shofet Haaretz
Hashev Gmul Al Ge'im, עד מתי רשעים ה' עד מתי רשעים יעלוזו,
Ad Matay Reshaim Hashem Ad Matay Reshaim Ya'alozu, punishment of רשעים, reshaim,
right? יביעו ידברו עתק יתאמרו כל פועלי און. Yabiu Yedabru Atek Yitamru
Kol Poalei Aven. So then it also talks about the oppression of
the Jews. עמך ה'
ידכאו ונחלתך יענו. Amcha Hashem Yedake'u Venachalatcha Ye'anu. אלמנה וגר יהרוגו ויתומים
ירצחו. Almana Veger Yaharogu Vitomim Yeratzachu. It's about, you know, the oppression
from
the—from the non-Jewish
nation. בינו בוערים בעם וכסילים מתי תשכילו. Binu Boarim Ba'am Uchsilim Matay
Tashkilu. השותל אוזן הלא ישמע אם יוצר עין הלא יביט. Hashoteil Ozen
Halo Yishma Im Yotzer Ayin Halo Yabit. God knows what's in your
heart. So—so אשרי הגבר אשר תייסרנו י-ה ומתורתך תלמדנו. Ashrei Hagever Asher
Teyasrenu Kah Umitoratcha Telamdenu. So what does this anything, any of this
have to do with סוכות? Sukkot So רש"י Rashi says, first of
all, it'll—it'll allude to the oppression that preceded, you know, in the
early periods of the—of the בית המקדש—or Beis HaMikdash that preceded one
minute—or that preceded the—the period between the two בתי מקדש, Batei Mikdash,
but also in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was certainly a period
of oppression from the non-Jews, from the Greeks and from the Romans,
etc. so that's one avenue, and רש"י Rashi *Rashi* also says געזונטהייט
*gesundheit*, and so that's the first half that we, you know, that
God has allowed us
to succeed, has sustained us even with the ongoing oppression from the
non-Jewish nations. Again, not exactly clear the direct tie-in to סוכות Sukkot,
*Sukkot*, but okay. But then the next part is the second half
of that מזמור *Mizmor*, and then ברביעית היו אומרים בינו בוערים בעם
*Barevi'it hayu omrim binu vo'arim ba'am*, which is, you know, God, those
you should understand God, those that would, those evil people, God knows
what's in your heart. So what does that have to do with
it? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that this is getting back to
a major סוכות Sukkot, *Sukkot* theme that it's the time, you know,
to be giving all the gifts to the poor and if you
collected מעשרות *Ma'asrot* and you bring it to ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and you're
supposed to be giving it, and people think, you know, okay, I'm
not going to give, nobody is going to know whether I do
these מצוות *Mitzvot* or not. So it's saying no, God knows what
you're doing, God knows what's in your heart. Don't think that you
can get away without actually doing this without there being consequences.
Okay, so again, pretty vague I would say and general, but רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* and not very unique to סוכות Sukkot. *Sukkot* a number
of these, but רש"י Rashi *Rashi* is trying to find a way
to tie it in. Whether you want to
say, Michael?
If you're talking about סוכות Sukkot *Sukkot*, it could be מצרים *Mitzrayim*,
the oppression could have been the Egyptians.
Yeah, that's pretty weak too. Okay. Anyway, so a lot of these
things in the middle here are about, you know, general remonstrances of
do the right thing. And a קהלת *Kohelet* theme? What?
Yeah, maybe it's a קהלת *Kohelet* theme.
I don't know. Okay. בחמישי bachamishi, היו אומרים *Bachamishi hayu omrim*, what
would they say on the fifth day? הסירותי מסבל שכמו *Hasiroti missevel
shikmo*.
So that is, let me just flip the page on that, פא
*Pei-Aleph*.
So this is all הרנינו לאלהים עוזנו הריעו לאלהי יעקב *Harninu L'Elohim
uzeinu hari'u L'Elohei Yaakov*. Okay, this is much more in a theme
of סוכות Succot, *Sukkot*. First of all, תרועות *Teruot* that we've been
talking about, second of all, think about the שמחת בית השואבה *Simchat
Beit HaShoeva*, listen to the next פסוק *Pasuk*: שאו זמרה ותנו תוף
כינור נעים עם נבל תקעו בחודש שופר בכסה ליום חגנו *Se'u zimrah
utnu tof kinnor na'im im navel tiku vachodesh shofar bakesseh l'yom hagenu*,
that sounds familiar. כי חוק לישראל הוא משפט לאלהי יעקב *Ki chok
l'Yisrael hu mishpat L'Elohei Yaakov*. So first of all, you have all
the playing of the musical instruments, and you have the allusion right
that we often the פסוק *Pasuk* we quote that relates back to,
you know, ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*. הסירותי מסבל שכמו כפיו מדוד תעבורנה
בערה קראת ואחלצך אענך בסתר רעם אבחנך על מי מריבה סלה שמע
*Hasiroti missevel shikmo kapav midud ta'avorna batzarah karata va'achaletzeka e'ancha beseter ra'am
evchancha al mei merivah selah shema*, okay, אם תשמע לי *im tishma
li* etc., המעלך מארץ מצרים *hama'alcha me'eretz Mitzrayim*. There you go, explicit
reference to יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim. *Yetziat Mitzrayim*. הרחב פיך ואמלאהו *Harchav
picha va'amaleihu*, right, open up your mouth, I will fill it, again,
about sustenance, rain, you know, the future agricultural year, okay, etc. So
that is much more obviously in the סוכות Sukkot *Sukkot* theme.
Okay, keeping on.
Right, and רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says explicitly it's about the water that
we're praying for at this time. You open up your mouth and
I will give you blessing etc. בששי היו אומרים ימוטו כל מוסדי
ארץ *Bashishi hayu omrim yamutu kol mosdei aretz*, all the foundations of
the earth will move, will shatter. What does that so what does
that mean? What's that relevant? So that's פב *Pei-Bet*, let me just
flip the collection, that's the next מזמור *Mizmor*. Wait
one minute. בקרב אלהים ישפוט עד מתי תשפטו עול ופני רשעים תשאו
סלה שפטו דל ויתום עני ורש הצדיקו *Bekerev Elohim yishpot ad matai
tishpetu avel upnei resha'im tise'u selah shiftu dal veyatom ani varash hatzdiku*.
So that's explicitly about taking care of the poor, right? פלטו דל
ואביון מיד רשעים הצילו לא ידעו ולא יבינו בחשיכה יתהלכו ימוטו כל
מוסדי ארץ אני אמרתי אלהים אתם ובני עליון כולכם אכן כאדם תמותון
וכאחד השרים תיפולו *Paletu dal ve'evyon miyad resha'im hatzilu lo yade'u velo
yavinu bachasheicha yithalchu yamutu kol mosdei aretz ani amarti Elohim atem uvnei
elyon kulchem achen ke'adam temutun uke'achad hasarim tipolu*. Okay, which is again
a little bit of the קהלת *Kohelet* theme, a little depressing. But
it also has עני ורש הצדיקו *ani varash hatzdiku*, which is about
again the concern of the poor, which is particularly a high, you
know, something that is underscored at this time, taking care of them,
giving the תרומות ומעשרות *Terumot uMa'asrot*, you know, at this time of
and making sure you give, you know, לקט שכחה ופאה *Leket Shichcha
uPe'ah* all of the gifts to the poor. Okay. So and now
to finish this up, בששי היו אומרים *bashishi hayu omrim*, oh we
just did that. ואם חל שבת באחד מהם *ve'im chal Shabbat be'echad
mehem*. Okay, so those are the six days of חול המועד Chol
HaMoed. *Chol HaMoed*. Now let's say שבת *Shabbat* falls out during חול
המועד Chol HaMoed. *Chol HaMoed*, it's not on a first day יום
טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*, so then you're not, so the implicit
assumption is is that שבת *Shabbat* the מזמור *Mizmor* of שבת *Shabbat*
will take precedence, although before we learned ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* takes
precedence over שבת *Shabbat*, that's to announce that it's ראש חודש *Rosh
Chodesh*. But if it's between שבת *Shabbat* and חול המועד Chol HaMoed,
סוכות Sukkot, *Chol HaMoed Sukkot*, שבת *Shabbat* is going to take precedence.
So which one of these מזמורים mizmorim *mizmorim* will you not say
if שבת *Shabbat* falls out on a middle day? So it says
so which one do you not say? ואם חל שבת באחד מהם
ימוטו ידחה *Ve'im chal Shabbat be'echad mehem yamutu yidcheh*. The last one
ימוטו *yamutu* is pushed away, maybe also a little bit of a
I don't know if this is the reason, but ימוטו *yamutu* means
to move, right, ימוטו כל מוסדי ארץ *yamutu kol mosdei aretz*, so
ימוטו *yamutu* is the one that gets pushed away. But anyway, the
point is if שבת *Shabbat* falls out in a middle day, so
what you do is it's sort of like a domino effect. If
שבת *Shabbat* falls out on day three, so what you would have
said on day three you say on day four, what you would
have said on day four you say on day five, etc. etc.,
and the one that is the odd man out at the end
is ימוטו *yamutu*. what you would have said on day four you
say on day five, what you would have said on day five
you'd say on day six, and what you would have said on
day six on day six doesn't get said, so that's the last
one, so it's a domino effect, it just pushes everything down the
road and then the last one is the one that does not
get said. Okay, so that's the basic point here about which ones
are said each day, but the effect of שבת *Shabbat*. Now again
the point is, well, why do you have to choose? If you
say a separate תקיעות *tkiyot* for each separate מוסף *musaf*, it means
a separate
מזמור *mizmor* for each separate מוסף *musaf*, you will wind up saying
both. You don't have to push one off. So again this makes
it once again clear that even on a day you have multiple
מוספים *musafim* like שבת חול המועד Chol HaMoed *Shabbat Chol HaMoed*, you're
only going to do one שיר *shir* and only going to do
one set of תקיעות *tkiyot* because the שיר *shir* and the תקיעות
*tkiyot* are intertwined. So that's just the point of the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* and then I'll take the questions. So רב ספרא מנח בסימנא
*Rav Safra manach be-simana*, רב ספרא *Rav Safra* gave a little acronym
for you to remember which are the מזמורי תהלים *Mizmorei Tehillim* that
you say on the different days of חול המועד Chol HaMoed, סוכות
Sukkot, *Chol HaMoed Sukkot*. What's the acronym?
So הומבבי *Humbabi*. So it's just the first, הומבבי *Humbabi*. So you
just look at it: הבו לה' *Havu l'Hashem*, ולרשע אמר *U'lerasha amar*,
מי יקום לי *Mi yakum li*, and now he though had, if
you notice the ה *he*, he reversed the order. He had הסירותי
*Hasiroti* first and then בינו בוערים בעם *Binu Bo'arim Ba'am* and then
ימותו כמותי ארץ *Yemotu K'mosei Aretz*. So he had our order but
reversed the two, בינו *Binu* and הסירותי *Hasiroti*. Okay, so I'm sorry
no, רב ספרא *Rav Safra* had the one that we had, הומבהי
*Humbahi*. I'm sorry, I skipped a line. רב ספרא מנח בסימני *Rav
Safra manach be-simani* הומבהי *Humbahi*. So he had the order we had:
בינו בוערים *Binu Bo'arim*, הסירותי *Hasiroti*, שכמוני *Shichmoni*, ימותו *Yemotu*. That was
רב ספרא *Rav Safra*. רב פפא מנח בסימנא *Rav Pappa manach be-simana*
הומבבי *Humbabi*. So he reversed the ב *bet* and the ה *he*.
He first had הסירותי *Hasiroti* and then he had בינו בוערים בעם
*Binu Bo'arim Ba'am* like sounds like Hamurabi, הומבבי *Humbabi*. וסימנך *Ve-simanch*, the
way you should remember which one רב ספרא *Rav Safra* said and
which one רב פפא *Rav Pappa* said, so אמבוהא דספרי *Ambuha de-sifrei*.
So there's a phrase which is like the אמבוהא *Ambuha*, which is
like the crowds that gather in front of the סופרים *sofrim*, which
means in front of the schoolteachers. You know, when it's pick-up time
at school, so you have all the crowds, it's very busy, all
the crowds are gathered when drop-off time and pick-up time. That's what
that phrase means. But אמבוהא דספרי *Ambuha de-sifrei*. So ספרי *sifrei* is
like ספרא *Safra*, and ספרא *Safra* said הומבהי *Humbahi*, that's אמבוהא *Ambuha*
as opposed to הומבבי *Humbabi*. So now you'll remember. I will test
you tomorrow. Anyway, the upshot of all that is that when it's
שבת חול המועד Chol HaMoed, *Shabbos Chol HaMoed*, you do the שבת
*Shabbos* one and you push off the next one. תיובתא דרב אחא
בר חנינא תיובתא *Tiyuvta de-Rav Acha bar Chanina tiyuvta*. This is another
contradiction of רב אחא בר חנינא *Rav Acha bar Chanina* which shows
again that if you have multiple מוספים *musafim*, you're only going to
do one שיר של יום *shir shel yom* and one set of
תקיעות *tkiyot*, and hence the consequence of if you're doing שבת *Shabbat*
on חול המועד Chol HaMoed, *Chol HaMoed*, the other ones get pushed
down the line. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ורב אחא בר
חנינא קרא מתניתא קמא *Ve-Rav Acha bar Chanina kra masnisa kama*? But
he had a פסוק *pasuk*, the פסוק *pasuk* says, you know, בני
אהרן הכהנים יתקעו בחצוצרות *B'nei Aharon ha-Kohanim yitke'u ba-chatzotzrot*, and there was
a ברייתא *baraita* that said it means everything is according to the
מוספים *musafim*, which sounds like you do something increased when you have
multiple מוספים *musafim*, and you're telling us you only do one set
of תקיעות *tkiyot*, one שיר של יום *shir shel yom*. What do
you do about that ברייתא *baraita*? So אמר רבינא *Amar Ravina*, so
says רבינא *Ravina*, לומר שמעריכים בתקיעות *Lomar she-ma'arichim bi-tkiyot*. What it means
you increase based on the number of מוספים *musafim* is not another
set of תקיעות *tkiyot*, not another שיר של יום *shir shel yom*,
but when you do the תקיעות *tkiyot*, you do them longer, you
play the notes longer to indicate that it's a double day, but
you don't do a double set. רבנן Rabbanan. דקיסרי משמיה דרב אחא
אמרי *Rabbanan de-Keisari mishmei de-Rav Acha amri*, and the rabbis of Caesarea
say in the name of רב אחא *Rav Acha*, לומר שמרבין בתוקעים
*Lomar she-marbin be-tokim*.
You don't have another set of תקיעות *tkiyot*, you add more players,
you add more people blowing the trumpet, but you still only do
one set and you have to choose, you know, it's one identity.
Okay, then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says just as to end this
discussion, ואנן דאית לן תרי יומי היכי עבידנא *Va-anan de-it lan trei
yomei heichi avidnan*? We who have two days of יום טוב Yom
Tov *Yom Tov*, what do we do? Now what's the question? I
mean, what do we do? What does two days of יום טוב
Yom Tov *Yom Tov* have to do between choosing like which like
if it's a double מוסף *musaf*? I understand. So the question is
this is really a question by analogy, it's not the same question
like a double day like שבת חול המועד Chol HaMoed *Shabbos Chol
HaMoed*, which one do we pick. It's really an analogous question of
having to choose by a doubling, but it's a very different type
of a doubling, and what it's asking is, what do we do
when we have on חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*, you've got today is
day three and day four, right, as it were of חול המועד
*Chol HaMoed*, right? The first day of חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*, which
day is it really? It's really day two of חול המועד *Chol
HaMoed*, but based on our ספיקא דיומא safeka d'yoma? *sfeika de-yoma*, it's
also sort of like maybe day one of חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*,
right? So what do we do in terms of the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is asking in terms of saying the פסוקים pesukim *psukim* for
the מוסף *musaf* in the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei. *Shmoneh Esreh* of
מוסף *musaf*? Which one do we highlight?
Okay, and
you
So which one are we going to do? Are we going to
do the day we really know it to be, you know, or
are we going to do the day based on well maybe it's
tomorrow? So if you have to choose, now we know of course
that what we do is we say both פסוקים. pesukim But the
גמרא Gemara, doesn't know that yet. So just got through this discussion,
right, about about choosing one identity of the day. So which identity
do we choose when we have to say the פסוקים pesukim of
the מוסף in חול המועד if we have this whole ספיקא דיומא?
safeka d'yoma, So which would we do?
So אביי אמר שני ידחה. Abaye amar sheni yidachei. אביי Abaye says
you push off the second day of חול המועד, meaning, I mean
the second day of יום טוב, Yom Tov, meaning
when you start on,
sorry, so if it's סוכות Sukkot, here, right, if it's day one
of יום טוב, Yom Tov. and then סוכות, Sukkot, right, יום טוב
Yom Tov. and day two, and then we have,
right, סוכות, Sukkot anyway then you have חול המועד. Okay, so if
you, so this is you know, this is day, this is,
this is day two, this is day three of סוכות. Sukkot Okay,
and then you have four, five, six, seven, and then you have
שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. Okay, and these are the days of חול
המועד. So what אביי Abaye says is שני ידחה. sheni yidachei. You
just ignore day two of סוכות Sukkot and you start saying the
קרבנות korbanot of each day three, four, five, six, seven. Okay.
Yeah, yeah, we're talking about, it's not in the גמרא Gemara but
רש"י's Rashi bringing it in on the side. So he says, okay
you know what, this day we were treating as a יום טוב
Yom Tov because of two days of יום טוב, Yom Tov, but
here go back to the normal counting that we know is the
real counting, you know, based on this being the first day יום
טוב. Yom Tov So forget about day two. Say the קרבנות korbanot
of each day three, four, five, six, seven. That's what אביי Abaye
says. One minute. רבא אמר שביעי ידחה. Rava amar shevii yidachei. רבא
Rava says no, you get here, here we start acting as if
this were day one because we did a ספיקא דיומא, and this
is the first day of real חול המועד, so we treat this
as if it's day two, three, four, five, three, four, five, six,
and you just never say the seventh day of חול המועד in
the שמונה עשרה. Okay, so you lose a day of קרבנות? korbanot?
What? Yeah, well we're a day off because we really know that
this is day one. אביי's Abaye makes more sense 'cause אביי gets
us back to what we really know. Of course you could say
it undermines the status of this as יום טוב. Yom Tov, So
רבא Rava says you just start here and you let seven fall
off the edge. Okay?
The קרבנות. korbanot. You mean the verses.
The פסוקים psukim that we say in the מוסף, right. So that's
what he
says. תניא כוותיה דרבא, Tanya k'vatiei d'Rava, we learn like רבא, Rava,
אם חל שבת באחד מהן ימותי ידחה. im chal Shabbat b'echad meihen,
yamotei yidachei. So the גמרא Gemara sees that as an analogous point
to רבא, Rava, which is if שבת falls out on חול המועד,
you just push everything down the line. So here too it's like
obviously you could say there's a different logic that should apply in
these two cases, but the גמרא Gemara says it would be a
similar point. יום טוב Yom Tov. came in on the second day
of חול המועד, it pushes everything down the line, seven falls off
the
edge. אתקין אמימר בנהרדעא דמדלגי דילוגי, Atkin Ameimar b'Nehardea d'medalgei dilugei, that
you jump, you jump back, which basically means we do what we
do. We say, you start on the second day, you should
be
saying nine on the second day, that would undermine the status of
יום טוב, but you should be saying three, but you jump back
and you also do two, so you say two and three here,
and three and four here, et cetera, et cetera. Okay, and that's
what we do. רש"י Rashi says has a similar discussion about what
do we do by קריאת התורה k'riat HaTorah in the, you know,
when we read during חול המועד, what פסוקים do we read? So
רש"י Rashi says that you read three and four for, you read
like the double day at the end, you know, let's say it
was here. So this day is a day of, place there's two
three-day, right? So רש"י Rashi says what you do is you read
two and three for the רביעי, revii, and what do you read
for the first three? For the first three רש"י Rashi says you
do two, three, four, and then you go back and you do
two, three.
תוספות Tosafot says you do, what you do is you do this
is for ראשון, rishon, this is for שני, this is for שלישי,
shelishi, this is for רביעי. revii. You do two, three, two, three.
Okay, רש"י Rashi, says you do two, three, four, and then two,
three. What do we actually do? Anybody know?
We go ahead.
Right. So that's what, so that's what, so that's what רש"י says.
Let me just check the here, by the קריאת התורה. k'riat HaTorah.
It's דף. First day says two, and then three, and then four,
and then two and three. That's what רש"י says. תוספות Tosafot says
you would do two, three, two, three. What do we do on
הושענא רבה? Hoshana Rabbah? We go through the very end.
Five, six, seven, no, so we go back, right, so it's not
consistent, right, we go we got to go back, five, six, seven,
and then six, seven. So תוספות Tosafot doesn't like the fact that
we're inconsistent according to רש"י's approach because we can't do six, seven,
eight, because then it would be into שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret.
Okay, yeah, so the מוסף is not identical with the תורה Torah
reading.
Well it's identical with the רביעי, revii, with the final קרא of
the תורה Torah reading,
right.
And then the other question is,
why don't they just keep the way that we have it normally?
Like, in other words, we switch days, you know, like the Tuesday
one with a different day. You know what I'm saying? What? Meaning,
meaning these are all מזמורים we say on a Wednesday, but it's
out of order.
No, not all of them, and they're specific to... Oh, you mean
what's the idea of the specific order? Yeah, I don't get the
order.
And then why don't we do that?
Well, no, but that's what we just said. מנהג הגר"א is to
do that. It's to say, it's to say the special ones that
they would say for the day. Yeah, I don't know. Alright, I
think that, I have to double check, but I'm fairly sure that
you would actually say
the, although it doesn't fit with the גמרא Gemara about the חומ"ש
Chumash by ראש השנה, where
the... whether you would say by the תמיד, Tamid, whether you would
say the normal one by the תמיד tamid or whether you would
say the one that is unique to the day. Pretty positive that
in the רמב"ם Rambam it says... I have to double check. He
says that you would say the normal one by the תמיד, tamid
which could... so what we say isn't wrong, it's just that you
would also say the special one. Why don't you say both? I
don't know. But anyway, I have to double check that.
Okay. And then someone says here the רמב"ם Rambam says שביעי דווקא.
shvi'i davka.
Okay,
I don't know. Let's go on. Next משנה. Mishnah. יום טוב הראשון
של חג, Yom Tov Harishon Shel Chag, so top of נ"ה ע"ב.
nun-hei amud beis. יום טוב הראשון של חג היו
שם י"ג פרים אילים שנים ושעיר אחד.
Yom Tov Harishon Shel Chag hayu sham yud-gimmel
parim eilim shnayim v'sa'ir echad. So this is just straight from the
פסוקים that you would have, start the מוסף would be 13 bulls,
2 rams, and 1 goat which would be the חטאת. chatas. The
rest would be an עולה. olah.
נשתיירו שם
י"ד כבשים nishtayru sham yud-dalet kvasim and there would be 14 sheep.
Now, that would be left as it were, I mean it all
depends on where you start, לשמונה משמרות. l'shmonah mishmarot. So basically there
would be 24 משמרות, mishmarot, accordingly would be divided into 24 groups.
Each group would serve a week. Which would mean basically you would
serve two weeks out of the year, a little bit more obviously.
And
on the רגלים Regalim though, all of the groups, since everybody's supposed
to be עולה לרגל oleh l'regel anyway, all of the groups are
serving in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. All the כהנים. kohanim. It
would be very crowded. I don't know how they would figure out
to select, because you know, some representation of all the groups. I'm
not sure how they would do it. Now, what they would also
do is they distributed the קרבנות korbanot each day, one animal per
group of כהנים. kohanim. And that group, what if you remember what
we learned in יומא Yoma is that, you know, even when you
just have one animal like the תמיד in the morning or something,
you divide it up into sections and multiple people got involved in
it. It wasn't just a one-person job. So you had 24 groups,
each one got one different animal of the מוסף. Okay. And there's
a benefit of, well, we'll see in a minute about, you know,
about getting the animals and then dividing the, they wouldn't have any
meat, but what they would have is they would have the skin
at least of the animal, there'd be that benefit. But anyway, but
they divide the animals of the מוסף. So, one animal per group.
However, they'd be more than, they'd
be more than 24 animals.
There's 13 bulls, 2 rams, 15, 1 goat, 16, and
14 sheep, 30. So every group would get one, and then there'd
be six animals left. So some groups would get two animals, okay?
And that's what it just discusses, that each day there would be
double, you know, different groups would, there would be a certain number
of groups that would get double. But the numbers would change because
the number of cows would go down. Now, this is a little
bit strange because if the number of cows are changing, you would,
it would be easier to discuss the doubling, that the cows were
the last thing and they would get fewer. But anyway, it's sort
of focusing it as that the last thing we distribute are the
sheep. So the question is which group would also get an additional
sheep in addition to what it just got? Was it cows and
sheep? Well, right, we'll talk about that in a minute. So, נשתיירו
שם י"ד כבשים לשמונה משמרות. nishtayru sham yud-dalet kvasim l'shmonah mishmarot. So
when you got up to the sheep, there were 14 sheep left
for the eight groups.
ביום ראשון ששה מקריבים שנים שנים. byom rishon shishah makrivim shnayim shnayim.
So the first day, there would be six that would get to
bring two animals, because you would have everybody done and you'd be
left with six sheep. So six groups would get to bring two
קרבנות. korbanot. והשאר אחד אחד, v'hashar echad echad, and everybody else only
gets to bring one קרבן. korban. בשני, bashaini, on the second day,
so because you have one fewer bull, so if you distribute the
sheep at the end, you've only have five sheep left over. חמישה
מקריבים שנים שנים והשאר אחד אחד. hamishah makrivim shnayim shnayim v'hashar echad
echad. בשלישי, bashlishi, on the third day, ארבעה מקריבים שנים שנים, arba'ah
makrivim shnayim shnayim, four groups get to do two, והשאר אחד אחד.
v'hashar echad echad. ברביעי, barvi'i, on the fourth day, שלושה מקריבים שנים
שנים, shloshah makrivim shnayim shnayim, three groups get to do two, והשאר
אחד אחד v'hashar echad echad and everybody else gets to do one.
בחמישי, on the fifth day, שנים מקריבים שנים שנים, shnayim makrivim shnayim
shnayim, only two groups get to do two, double up, והשאר אחד
אחד v'hashar echad echad and everybody else only does one. בשישי, bashishi,
on the sixth day, so אחד מקריב שנים שנים והשאר אחד אחד,
echad makriv shnayim shnayim v'hashar echad echad, only one group gets to
do two, and everybody else one. בשביעי, bashvi'i, on the seventh day
of סוכות, Sukkot, כולם שווים, kulam shavim, then there's only exactly 24
animals. Okay, and everybody only gets one.
בשמיני... bashmini... So you did not you started the cycle all over
again. Now what does it mean start you know what it start
the cycle over again. Well presumably what we've been saying here is
is that when you say which groups get double, okay, it's presumably
we want to make sure that a group that yesterday got double
doesn't get double today, right, do you understand like we shift which
groups were going to give the extra ones to. So every day
sort of takes into account how do we distribute it the day
before. But when you get to שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, you start
by the slate clean and you do a new a new lottery
to decide which group gets which animals and has nothing to do
with who got yesterday. אמרו Amru מי שהקריב פרים היום לא יקריב
למחר אלא חוזרים חלילה. mi shehikriv parim hayom lo yakriv le-machar ela
chozrim chalila. Now just to make it more confusing there's two things
that we want to do to take into account on during חול
המועד or whatever during סוכות Sukkot based on what happened yesterday. One
is that if you got double yesterday you don't get doubles today,
but the other is if you got a cow yesterday, a bull
yesterday, you don't get a bull today because a bull was huge
and it wouldn't be fair and there weren't enough bulls to go
around. There were only thirteen bulls and then twelve and then eleven
and ten. So therefore we want to make sure that
you don't that if you got a bull yesterday you're not going
to get another bull today. And if you got a two yesterday
you're only going to get one today. So if you think about
it I'm trying I was trying to figure out a good visual
representation of this. You have to think of like two concentric like
circles. If you sort of think about it if you have like
like
you have your twenty-four כהנים Kohanim here... 15,
16,
whatever, 17, 18, okay, 19, 20, wow, 21, 22, 23, okay, whatever,
24, we'll make this a little bigger. If you think about you
have them all as a group and you think about if you
have like two wheels, two circles, right? So you have one wheel
which is basically like the פרים, parim, right? So it's like you
know פר, par, פר, par, פר, par, פר, par, there'd be thirteen
on the first day, right? So then what you want to be
doing is, oops, פר, par, פר, par, I don't know if this
is helping anybody, it's sort of helping me. Anyway I can't even
write that way. Anyway you've got like one wheel here, right? So
this is who got the פר par the first day. So the
next day you're going to turn the wheel and you're going to
sort of start here, right, and then it's going to go like
that and then it's going to go like that and then it's
going to go you're going to constantly be turning that. That's the
distribution of you know of today but then there's also the issue
about you know about who gets like
a double. So because wait a minute and now I've like
confused myself. No you have not. Oh thank you
for telling me I haven't confused myself.
The
double is the next one after the פר. par.
Yeah but if you did the other one like
that I guess that would work. No that wouldn't work, you see,
because if you then did the next the remainder of the thing,
would that work? Who's getting double? So if you did the remainder
the remainder was you started with thirteen, right? The remainder went all
the way like this so six of these guys these six got
double and they got the פר. par. And then you moved the
wheel thirteen. No it's going to get off because you have to
move the the פר par wheel you have to move thirteen to
start here but the double wheel you only want to move six.
So you get can you get
if you had a פר par yesterday,
yes, you had a פר par yesterday, yes, it's technically except for
one guy not supposed to get a פר par again but you
could still get double. Yes.
See that's the problem. If you want to do the פר par
you start the פר par thing here but if you want to
actually then figure out who gets double you're only going to shift
six. So you have to like figure out you have to like
have two separate two separate charts, like one chart to make sure
you can figure it out but basically it's one chart to make
sure that that you're moving the number of פרים parim which is
not the same and then a separate chart to make sure that
one minute you know if you got double yesterday we're having a
separate move groups one through six got double yesterday today groups seven
through twelve or seven through eleven are getting double you know and
so on. What?
Yes, I guess you can get the double פר. par. I mean
you can get the פר par and then the
כבש keves but
put another wheel inside it.
Exactly. Put a third wheel inside it, somehow each item is different
than the... Exactly that's the basic point. Yeah you have to move
the wheels differently to get figure
out. Okay anyway. נימא מתניתין, Neima matnitin, says the גמרא, Gemara, let's
say our משנה Mishna
is רבי Rabbi ולא רבנן. v'lo Rabbanan. Now by the way oh.
Let me just do the math for you about the פר, par,
so there would be over over the seven days there would be
70 פרים. parim. Okay, you'll do the math. So by by the
way, you want to know a cute math fact
if you have to add up a sequence of numbers? So if
you're adding up 13, 12, 11, 10, 9, 8, 7, okay, these
are
the seven days of סוכות, Sukkot right? Here's a quick way you
can add them up. 20, 20, 20, 10. So you've got
70. There's actually
a formula. Okay, anyway, fine. So there's 70 פרים parim and there
are 24 groups. So each group will get three plus three bulls,
except for two, because 3 times 24 is 72. So part of
the idea that you start a new lottery on שמיני עצרת Shemini
Atzeret is you don't say, oh look, one of these two groups
didn't get a bull, let's make sure we give a bull to
one of them on שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. No, we're starting everything
fresh, we don't take into account anything that we did before. So
the גמרא gemara says, נימא מתניתין רבי היא ולא רבנן, Neyma Matnisin
Rabbi hi velo Rabbanan, let's say our משנה Mishnah is רבי Rabbi
and not the רבנן. Rabbanan דתניא, De'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא:
פר הבא בשמיני, Par ha-ba b'shemini, the bull that they had on
שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, תחילה מפיסין עליו, techilah mafisin alav, you start
a completely new lottery and you don't take into into account anybody
who got the oxen for the
last for the last seven days. דברי רבי, Divrei Rabbi, that's what
רבי Rabbi says. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, no, אחת משתי משמרות שלא
שילשו בפרים עושה אותה. achas mi-shtei mishmarot she-lo shilshu b'parim osa otah.
No, we take one of the two groups that did not that
was left over, that did not get three oxen over over סוכות,
Sukkot, they will get this extra this bull on ראש השנה on
on שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. So you do take into account and
you give it to one of the two remaining groups. גמרא gemara,
says no, אפילו תימא רבנן, afilu teima Rabbanan, it could be even
the רבנן Rabbanan, that maybe we do only give it to one
of the two groups. Ah, how about the משנה Mishnah says that
that says that you do a new lottery? So it says, אטו
שתי משמרות לאו אפוסי בעי? Atu shtei mishmarot lav afusei ba'ei? So
you have to do a lottery between the two groups. So it
didn't say you maybe don't do a completely new lottery, okay, so
you but but you don't give it to the next one on
the line, you give it to one of the two and you
do a lottery between them. But the general assumption of the גמרא
gemara is that פיס בפני עצמו שמיני עצרת payis bifnei atzmo Shemini
Atzeret means do you completely do a new lottery. Okay, כמאן אזלא
הא דתניא, k'man azla ha de'tanya, who's it going like that which
we taught in a ברייתא? כל המשמרות שונות ומשלשות, kol hamishmarot shonot
u-meshaleshot, all of the משמרות mishmarot got double and three, meaning of
the of the bulls we're talking about now, חוץ משתי משמרות chutz
mi-shtei mishmarot except for two of them, ששונות ואין משלשות, she-shonot ve-ein
meshaleshot, that only got double and not triple. So נימא רבי ולא
רבנן? nema Rabbi velo Rabbanan? So let's say it's רבי Rabbi and
not the רבנן, Rabbanan because according to the רבנן Rabbanan. only one
group would be left at the end that didn't get triple. You'd
make sure that one of the two remaining groups would also would
get. So for him only one group would be left at the
very end. גמרא Gemara. says no, אפילו תימא רבנן, afilu teima Rabbanan,
it could be even the רבנן. Rabbanan מאי לא שילשו, mai lo
shilshu, what does it mean it didn't get triple? בפרי החג, b'parei
ha-chag, it means you didn't get triple amongst the bulls that were
brought on סוכות, maybe plus שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret one more group
would get. Fine, but of those brought on סוכות, two groups would
not get triple. ומאי קמשמע לן, u-mai kamashma lan, what's it teaching
me? הא קמשמע לן, ha kamashma lan, מי שהקריב פרי היום לא
יקריב למחר אלא חוזר חלילה, mi she-hikriv parei ha-yom lo yakriv le-machar
ela chozer chalilah, to tell you that if you brought yesterday a
bull you don't bring it today, you keep on moving forward in
the line. Okay, so anyway there is this debate of רבי and
the רבנן
whether of the last two that did not get triple on שמיני
עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, would you give it to one of them or
would you start fresh completely. אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, הני
שבעים פרים כנגד מי? haneh shiv'im parim k'neged mi? Here's the famous
גמרא, Gemara what?
One משמר mishmar gets four and one gets two.
One gets four, oh well, one might get four by שמיני עצרת.
Shemini Atzeret. By שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, it's possible that one of
the two remaining got, but the greater chances are that one would
get four and two of them would get two. That's true. Okay,
אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, הני שבעים פרים כנגד מי? haneh
shiv'im parim k'neged mi? These 70 bulls, what do they represent? כנגד
שבעים אומות, k'neged shiv'im umot, the 70 nations. פר יחידי למה לי?
par yechidi lamah li? What's the one bull on שמיני עצרת? Shemini
Atzeret? כנגד אומה יחידה, k'neged uma yechidah, the single nation amongst the
70 nations. משל למלך בשר ודם, mashal le-melech basar va-dam,
it can be compared to a king of flesh and blood, שאמר
לעבדיו, she-amar la'avadav, who said to his servants, עשו לי סעודה גדולה,
asu li se'udah gedolah, make for me a great feast. וליום
אחרון, u-le-yom acharon, and on his last day, אמר לאוהבו, amar le-o'havo,
he said to the beloved, the person, עשו לי סעודה קטנה, asu
li se'udah ktanah, you know what, for now it's the last day,
let's have just a private meal, כדי שאהנה ממך, k'dei she-aneh mimcha,
so that I can have some special time, some you know, intimate
time with you. And that of course is you know, the very
famous מדרש, midrash, not just on the פרים, parim, but to try
to give some significance to שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, which is a
חג chag that often is not clear what its function is, what
its identity is. So this time, like after all of the big
to-do of סוכות and everything, we have this very private quiet time
with God before we transition out of the whole ימים נוראים Yamim
Noraim period. But here it's also contrasting not just to the you
know, to the... the excitement, the largeness of the period that preceded
but the sense of the more universalist aspect. And particularly touches on
the fact that סוכות is a universalist יום טוב as well. And
רש"י underscores that if you look at רש"י, he says שבעים פרים,
Shivim Parim, it's about ten lines down in the wide lines, beginning
of the line. פרה החג שבעים הם חוץ משל שמיני כנגד שבעים
אומות לכפר עליהם שירדו גשמים בכל העולם לפי שנדונו בחג על המים.
Pareh He-chag shivim hem chutz mi-shel shmini k'neged shivim umot l'chaper aleihem
she-yeirdu g'shamim be-chol ha-olam le-fi she-nidonu be-chag al ha-mayim. It's not just
a Jewish יום טוב, right? And some of the הפטרות haftarot that
we read on סוכות is about all the nations will come to
celebrate חג הסוכות, Chag Ha-sukkot, and about the fact that they will
have rain if they come to celebrate חג הסוכות. Chag Ha-sukkot. So
there's certainly the universal aspect of the need of rain. And also
let's face it, פסח Pesach is very specific,
particularistic. It's about יציאת מצרים. Whereas סוכות, even though כי בסכות הושבתי,
Ki va-sukkot hoshavti,
fundamentally it's about
recognizing that our vulnerability and that we're under God's protection and that's
certainly underscored by the need when the need for rain
and how much we need God's presence and God's protection. And that
was a reality that we had in the מדבר, Midbar, but it's
not fundamentally a historical יום טוב. So it fundamentally has a real
profound universal dimension to it, which is reflected in a lot of
the הפטרות. haftarot. So the שפת אמת S'fat Emet says, let it
be universal, but at least one day at the end, let's reconnect
to that unique relationship. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, said רבי
יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: אוי להם לעובדי כוכבים שאבדו ואין יודעים מה אבדו.
Oy lahem le-ovdei kochavim she-avdu
ve-ein yod'im mah avdu. Woe to the nations of the world that
they lost without realizing what they've lost. בזמן שבית המקדש קיים מזבח
מכפר עליהם. Bizman she-Beit Ha-mikdash kayam mizbe'ach mechaper aleihem. When the בית
המקדש Beit Ha-mikdash was around, we brought sacrifices for them. ועכשיו מי
מכפר עליהם? Ve-achshav mi mechaper aleihem? Now who's atoning for them? Meaning
at least we know we don't have a בית המקדש, Beit Ha-mikdash,
so we understand what we've lost, so we work at addressing it,
תורה Torah and מעשים טובים Ma'asim Tovim and so on. But there
it was all being done for them without their awareness, and now
what are they left with? So, but it still is interesting, I
should say, that concern, that universalist concern, that's still there. There's other
גמרות gemaras which have a very antagonistic approach towards the non-Jews. There's
other things that are said about the שבעים shivim and the reason
it goes down. This is not antagonistic. It's for their sake, it's
a concern for the larger world. All right, next משנה. mishnah. בשלשה
פרקים בשנה היו כל המשמרות שוות באמורי הרגלים ובחילוק לחם הפנים. Be-shloshah
prakim ba-shanah hayu kol ha-mishmarot shavot be-imurei ha-regalim u-ve-chiluk lechem ha-panim. So
now that we're talking about how on סוכות everybody was together and
it was all divided equally, we're going to say that this was
actually at three times during the year, meaning at all the three
רגלים, regalim, all the משמרות mishmarot would work together in the בית
המקדש Beit Ha-mikdash and they would divide everything equally. So they would
be equal באמורי רגלים. be-imurei regalim. אמורי Imurei literally means the innerds,
the fats, but of course they wouldn't get the fats, that would
go on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So we'll see what the גמרא Gemara
says it means. It means that they would all be equal in
bringing up the קרבנות korbanot of the רגלים, regalim, the special קרבנות
korbanot of the מוספים and dividing the לחם הפנים. lechem ha-panim. Interesting,
although לחם הפנים lechem ha-panim was not unique to the רגלים, regalim,
they would equally divide it. Everybody would get a little piece of
bread of מצה matzah from the לחם הפנים lechem ha-panim during the
רגלים. regalim. בעצרת, Be-Atzeret, now on עצרת, Atzeret, which is not שמיני
עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, but in Tannaitic language it's שבועות, Shavuot, where you
would have the לחם הפנים lechem ha-panim which is made out of
מצה, matzah, but you'd also have the שתי הלחם, shtei ha-lechem, which
is part of the special קרבנות החג. korbanot ha-chag. So that would
be equally divided as well. And the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem was
made out of חמץ. chametz. So on עצרת, Atzeret, אומר לו, omer
lo, you would say to the כהן: kohen: הילך מצה הילך חמץ.
Heilech matzah heilech chametz. Here's your מצה, matzah, here's your tiny little
piece of מצה matzah from the לחם הפנים, lechem ha-panim, here's your
tiny little bit of חמץ chametz from the שתי הלחם. shtei ha-lechem.
משמר שזמנו קבוע הוא מקריב תמידים נדרים ונדבות. Mishmar she-zmano kavua hu
makriv temidim nedarim u-nedavot. Now, if it was your week,
סוכות or פסח Pesach fell out in what normally would have been
your week in the normal 24 cycle, so everybody shares the special
קרבנות korbanot that are unique to סוכות, or unique to פסח, Pesach,
or unique to שבועות, Shavuot, but our group, the group that should
have gone this week, whose regular time it was this week, we
get the regular קרבנות. korbanot. That we don't share. We still bring
the regular things. What are the regular things? תמידים, Temidim, the תמיד
of morning and afternoon, נדרים ונדבות nedarim u-nedavot if people are bringing
free-will sacrifices. It's not unique to the regal sacrifices, they're just bringing
their own personal קרבן. korban. ושאר קרבנות ציבור, Ve-sha'ar korbanot tzibbur, and
any other קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur that is not unique to the
regal, what that includes we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara ומקריב את
הכל u-makriv et ha-kol and bring everything else. So we'll find out
in the גמרא Gemara what that includes that we haven't already said.
But I do have to tell you that it was a real
bonanza to get your week to be the רגל regel because even
though you say okay you share the
communal קרבן korban sacrifices, but if all of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael
has been עולה לרגל, oleh la-regel, this is when they're bringing the
sacrifices that they've been owing for the last, you know, six months.
So if you get to do all of that, it's a real
bonanza and if it's a shlo... meat, and even if mostly it
would be a, if it's an עולה, olah, at least you get
the skin; you know, so it would be a real bonanza to
get that to fall out in your week. Okay, let's see the
גמרא.
גמרא says, "Does that just rotate through year to year as you
went over 24 it shifts?"
"Yeah, yeah, so it would shift.
It wouldn't be over the course of..."
"Exactly, exactly, and when exactly the רגל regel would fall would also
shift. But yes, exactly, eventually it would all even out." אמורי הרגלים.
Emurei HaRegalim. The גמרא says, "The fats? שגבוה נינהו! shegavoa ninu! Those
go up on the altar! What do you mean that would be
divided?" Okay, because it sounds like we're talking about something you would
get direct benefit from, it talks about eating the לחם הפנים Lechem
HaPanim and so on. So אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, מה
שאמור ברגלים. mashe'amur biRegalim. Funny, funny way of saying it. The things
that are said. אמורי emurei doesn't mean the אמורים, emurim, but means
the things that are said relative to the רגלים. Regalim. Okay, which
again is pretty funny way of saying it. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
מניין שכל המשמרות שוות באמורי הרגלים? minayin shekol hamishmarot shavot be'emurei haRegalim?
There you get the phrase again. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so how
do you know that they all divided equally? ובא בכל אות נפשו
ושרת. ubah bekhol avat nafsho vesheret. So there is a פסוק that
is, Michael, can you hand me that חומש? Chumash? That is used
for the basis of this idea that on the רגל regel everybody
serves equally. Okay, so this is דברים י"ח, Devarim Yud-Chet, I'll just
read it to you.
וכי יבוא הלוי, vekhi yavo halevi,
now it says לוי Levi but חז"ל Chazal understand it to be
כהן kohen because it's going to be talking about serving in the
מקדש, Mikdash, מאחד שעריך מכל ישראל אשר הוא גר שם ובא בכל
אות נפשו me'achad she'arekha mikol yisrael asher hu gar sham uba bekhol
avat nafsho come according to his own will אל המקום אשר יבחר
ה' ושרת בשם ה' אלוהיו ככל אחיו הלוויים העומדים שם לפני ה'.
el hamakom asher yivchar Hashem vesheret beshem Hashem elohav kekhol echav halevi'im
ha'omedim sham lifnei Hashem.
He can serve, he can show up and serve. So the simple
sense of the verse, besides the simple sense talking about לויים, Levi'im,
is that anytime you show up you're free to come and serve.
But חז"ל Chazal read it that it's only the רגלים. Regalim. It
says מאחד שעריך, me'achad she'arekha,
it says one of your gates when everybody is in the same
gate, everybody is coming together. So that's the way they read it,
not just whenever you show up. חלק כחלק יאכלו לבד ממכריו על
האבות. chelek kechelek yokhelu levad mimkarav al ha'avot. He will eat, everybody
will eat, he will get an equal portion except for what was
sold to the fathers. Very strange phrase. So let's see what the
גמרא does with it. Okay, ובא בכל אות נפשו ושרת, ubah bekhol
avat nafsho vesheret, יכול אף בשאר ימות השנה כן? yakhol af bish'ar
yemot hashanah ken? Maybe even during the rest of the year he
can just show up? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse teaches מאחד
שעריך, me'achad she'arekha, one of your gates. לא אמרתי אלא בשעה שכל
ישראל נכנסין בשער אחד, lo amarti ela besha'ah shekol Yisrael nikhnasin besha'ar
echad, when everybody is coming in the same gate on the רגל.
regel. Now once we say he's entitled to serve, so another verse
tells us that who gets to eat from the קרבנות korbanot are
the people that served, that actually were entitled to bring the קרבנות.
korbanot. So if all of the groups are entitled to serve in
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash on the רגלים, Regalim, they're also entitled
to an equal portion of the קרבנות. korbanot. Now what we have
to do is: how do we know that it's only the special
קרבנות korbanot and where's this לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim coming in? So
let's just finish those דרשות. derashot. ובחילוק לחם הפנים, ubikhiluk Lechem HaPanim,
where do you know that he gets a portion of the לחם
הפנים? Lechem HaPanim? That's, so תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, מניין שכל המשמרות
שוות בחילוק לחם הפנים? minayin shekol hamishmarot shavot bikhiluk Lechem HaPanim? How
do you know that they get an equal portion? It's because by
the way, they're not really serving in the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim.
The לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim was put off, you know, the week
before. So they're not, it's not like they have equal service and
therefore equal division. It's also not unique to the רגל. regel. So
where's this idea that they get an equal portion in the
לחם הפנים? Lechem HaPanim? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, חלק כחלק יאכלו, chelek
kechelek yokhelu, they shall eat. כחלק עבודה, kechelek avodah, the same way
you get an equal portion in the עבודה, avodah, כך חלק אכילה,
kakh chelek akhilah, you get an equal portion in the eating. ומאי
אכילה? umai akhilah? What type of eating? אילימא קרבנות, ileima korbanot, if
it's the normal eating that comes with קרבנות, korbanot, מהתם נפקא, meihasam
nafka, you can learn it from over there. לכהן המקריב אותו לו
תהיה. lakohen hamakriv oto lo tihyeh. We already know that if you're
entitled to bring, to be מקריב, makriv, you're entitled to the eating.
So if we already said you're entitled to serve, implicitly is you're
entitled to eat from the things that you can do the עבודה
avodah for. So what is the only thing that you would be
eating that you didn't do the עבודה avodah for? Well, the only
thing that's only eating is לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim because the עבודה
avodah was done last week when it was put on the שולחן.
shulchan. Okay, so אלא לחם הפנים, ella Lechem HaPanim, so we're talking
about that you also get a portion of the לחם הפנים. Lechem
HaPanim. יכול אף בכל בז שבא מחמת הרגל ברגל? yakhol af bekhol
baz shebo machamat haregel baregel? Maybe if you get a portion of
the לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, which is not unique to the רגל,
regel, you get an equal portion in all of the things that
are brought on the רגל regel even if they're not unique to
the רגל? regel? תלמוד לומר, לבד ממכריו על האבות, levad mimkarav al
ha'avot, except for that which was sold to the fathers. מה מכרו
האבות
זה לזה? mah makhru ha'avot zeh lazheh? What did the fathers sort
of divide amongst themselves? Meaning that they sort of split up, you
know, they split up the rotation.
אני בשבתי ואתה בשבתך. ani beshabbati v'atah beshabbatekha. They split up the
rotation of the כהנים. kohanim. So we're not dealing with the general
issues of what you're entitled because of your rotation, because of the
normal things. This is only talking about what is unique to the
רגל. regel. And what's unique to the רגל, regel, with the one
exception of the לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, that's not unique to the
רגל regel but that also gets divided up. I must say that
it's a little bit bizarre because this is a פסוק in דברים
Devarim and you did not have yet 24 groups of כהנים kohanim
to divide up. I must say that it's a little bit bizarre
because this is a פסוק in דברים Devarim and you did not
have yet 24 groups of כהנים kohanim to divide this up and
so on and how they're exactly dealing with that issue, the גמרא
does not really explain. Okay, so that'll be it. Tomorrow is the
last day of the מסכתא.
masechta. I don't think we're gonna finish.